Register of the Charles Maynard Cooke papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- NAVAL CAREER OFFICE FILE, 1920-1950 (Boxes 16-25)
  Official correspondence, reports, memoranda, orders, vouchers, messages, notes, rosters, lists, conference papers, minutes, charts, maps, and diagrams accumulated by Cooke during his naval career. The organization of material, patterned as closely as possible after Cooke's own organization, begins with a chronological arrangement of the Navy Department orders affecting Cooke's duty assignments, continues with a chronological arrangement (by year, month, and day) of material dealing with general naval affairs, and concludes with an alphabetical arrangement of material related to major projects and assignments in which Cooke was involved. Citations to selected memoranda and reports have been added under many subseries in order to indicate the variety and significance of the material authored and collected by Cooke during his career.
  - Navy Department orders (change of duty), endorsements, and vouchers, 1928-1950 (Box 16)
  - General naval affairs, 1930-1949
    - 1930
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Midshipman Age Limits for Entrance in the U.S. Naval Academy," 1930 April 5.
    - 1931
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Selection for Promotion of Commissioned Officers in the United States Navy," 1931 May 12.
    - 1934
    - 1935
    - 1936
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Submarine Organization with the U.S. Fleet and the Assignment of Commanders," 1936 July 2, and "Battleship Design," 1936 December.
    - 1937
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Naval Aviation Policies," 1937 October 1.
    - 1938
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Fleet Organization," 1938 April 28, "Fleet War Plans," 1938 June 5, "Some Principles Affecting Zigzagging," 1938 June 5, and "Atlantic War Plans," 1938 October 7.
    - 1939
      Includes Crenshaw, R. S. "Steps to be Taken in the Event that England and France Enter the War Against Germany," 1939 September 1; and Cooke, C. M. "Organization and Command of Major Forces of the U.S. Fleet," 1939 November 16.
    - 1940
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Characteristics of Heavy Cruisers," 1940 March 23.
    - 1941
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Comments on Tentative War Plans 0-1 (Rainbow Three)," 1941 April 7.
    - 1942
    - 1943 (Box 17)
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Analysis of the Functions of Ground, Sea, and Air Forces in Time of War," 1943 July 9.
    - 1944
      Includes Cooke, C. M. "Naval Organization for Handling Operations and Logistics," 1944 February 8, and "The Navy's Job," 1944 May 27.
    - 1945
      Includes Office of Naval Intelligence. "Combatant Vessels of the Seven Principle Naval Powers," and "Number of Vessels Lost Incident to the Present War," 1945 January 1 and September 1; Strausz-Hupé, Robert. Outline of proposal to establish a research unit concerned with the study of seapower within the framework of national policy (letter from M. B. Gardner to Admiral Cooke attached), 1945 April 10; "Analysis of the Venezuelan Revolution of October 19, 1945," 1945 October 24; and "The Joint Chiefs of Staff Organization, World War II," 1945.
    - 1946
    - 1947
      Includes "Naval Effort in China," 1947 February.
    - 1948
      Includes Roster of Flag Officers, 1948 February 1; "Brief of Logistic Situation in Service Squadron Three on 15 February 1948, Prepared for the Occasion of the Turnover of Command of Naval Forces Western Pacific by Admiral C. M. Cooke, U.S. Navy, to Admiral O. C. Badger, U.S. Navy," 1948 February; and "Narrative History of Seventh Fleet and Naval Forces Western Pacific, 8 January 1946 - 24 February 1948," 1948 February.
    - 1949
    - Undated
      Includes lists of important personalities in Chinese cities.
  - Allied wartime conferences, 1943-1945
    - Casablanca Conference (2 bound volumes), 1943 January
      - Minutes, U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff meetings (Box 18)
      - Minutes, U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff meetings (presided over by the President)
      - Papers, Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Minutes, Anfa (Symbol) meetings
      - Minutes, Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
    - Trident Conference (Washington, D.C.) and Algiers Conference (bound volume), 1943 May
      - Papers (Trident), Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Minutes (Trident), White House meetings
      - Minutes (Trident), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Algiers), Algiers meetings
    - Quadrant Conference (Quebec) (bound volume), 1943 August
      - Papers, Combined Chiefs of Staff (Box 19)
      - Minutes, Citadel meetings
      - Minutes, Combined Chiefs of Staff
    - Sextant Conference (Cairo) and Eureka Conference (Teheran) (bound volume), 1943 November - December
      - Papers (Sextant), Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Minutes (Sextant), Plenary meetings
      - Minutes (Sextant and Eureka), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Eureka), Plenary and Military sessions
    - Octagon Conference (Quebec) and London Conference (bound volume), 1944 September
      - Messages, Supreme Allied Commanders (Box 20)
      - Papers (Octagon), Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Minutes (London), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Octagon), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Octagon), Plenary meetings
    - Argonaut Conference (Malta and Yalta) (bound volume), 1945 January
      - Papers, Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Messages, Supreme Allied Commanders
      - Minutes (Malta), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Yalta), Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes (Yalta), Tripartite military meetings
      - Minutes (Malta and Yalta), Plenary meetings
      - Minutes (Yalta), Tripartite Plenary meetings
    - Terminal Conference (Babelsberg/Potsdam) (bound volume), 1945 July
      - Papers, Combined Chiefs of Staff
      - Minutes, Combined Chiefs of Staff meetings
      - Minutes, Plenary meeting
      - Minutes, Tripartite military meeting
      - Minutes, U.S. - U.S.S.R. Chiefs of Staff meeting
  - Anti-submarine campaign, 1942-1943 (Box 21)
  - German Navy and Merchant Marine, Disposition of, 1945
    Correspondence, messages, and reports related to the work of the Tripartite (U.S. - Great Britain - U.S.S.R.) Commissions for Distribution of the German Navy and Merchant Marine.
  - Hoover Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of Government - Eberstadt Committee on National Security Organization, 1947-1948
    Briefing data, correspondence, and memoranda.
  - Military operations and planning, 1942-1945
    - European Theater
      - Volume I, 1942 April - September
        Includes (Marshall, G. C.), Chief of Staff. Memorandum for the President on the "Basis for Preparation of Attached Outline Plan for the Invasion of Western Europe," 1942 June(?); Marshall, G. C., and King, E. J. Memorandum for the President on the Sledgehammer - Roundup Operation, 1942 July 28; Marshall, G. C. "Torch," 1942 August 17; Cooke, C. M. "Operation Torch," 1942 August 24 and "Torch Operation," 1942 August 29; and King, E. J. "Directive for Participation of U.S. Atlantic Fleet in Operation Torch," 1942 September(?).
      - Volume II, 1942 September - 1944 January
        Includes Cooke, C. M. "Naval Command Set-up in U.K. for Cross-Channel Operations," 1943 October 7, and "Overlord - Rankin," 1943 October 8.
      - Volume III, 1944 January - 1945 August
        Includes Cooke, C. M. "U.S. Naval Forces for Overlord," 1944 January 14, and "Steps to Reduce the Determination of the German People to Continue the War," 1945 January 21.
    - Pacific Theater
      - Volume I, 1942 May - 1943 March (Box 22)
        Includes Marshall, G. C.; King, E. J.; and Arnold, H. H. Memorandum for the President on "Pacific Operations" ("sent" and "rejected" copies), 1942 July 12; Marshall, G. C. "Strategic Direction of Operations in Southwest Pacific," 1942 December 21; King, E. J. "Strategic Direction of Operations in the Southwest Pacific," 1942 December 30(?); and Cooke, C. M. "Moroccan Conference Trip, January 1943," 1943 January 31, and "A Pattern for the War in the Pacific," 1943 March 6.
      - Volume II, 1942 April - 1944 May
        Includes Cooke, C. M. "Future Campaign Operations in Pacific Ocean Areas," 1943 June 8, "Command Organization - Pacific," 1943 July 28, "Plans and Operations for the Pacific Campaign," 1943 September 5, and "Operations in the South - Southwest Pacific," 1943 September 16.
      - Volume III, 1944 May - 1945 March
        Includes Joint Chiefs of Staff. "Strategic Deployment of U.S. Forces Following the Defeat of Germany - JCS 521/9," 1945 January; and Cooke, C. M. "Future Operations in the War Against Japan," 1945 March 21, and "Blockade Against Japan and Establishment of Sea Communications to the Russian Maritime Provinces," 1945 March 22.
      - Volume IV, 1945 April - August
        Cooke, C. M. "The War Against Japan: Part Played by Russia," 1945 April 4, and "Command Set-up for Invasion of Japan," 1945 April 8; and (Joint Chiefs of Staff-?). Memorandum for the President on the Over-all Strategy for the Defeat of Japan, 1945 April 6.
    - China, India, Burma Theater, 1942-1945 (Box 23)
      Includes Miles, M. E. "SACO," 1943 April 1; and Headquarters, U.S. Forces, China Theater. (A. Wedemeyer-?). "Far East Strategy - 1945" (see also: Pacific Theater, Volume III, "Far East Strategy"), 1945 February.
  - Postwar military policy and planning, 1944-1946
    - General
    - Reorganization of the Department of Defense
  - Reports on the conduct of the war by Fleet Admiral Ernest J. King, 1944-1945
    - Official reports to the Secretary of the Navy
    - Report to the Congress in Joint Assembly (drafted by C. M. Cooke-?), 1945 January 24
  - Shipbuilding - Wartime production, 1941-1945
    Includes Cooke, C. M. "Application of Production to Strategical Requirements," speech before members of the War Production Board Council, 1942 October 20, and "Allocation of United States Built Landing Craft," 1942 October 29.
  - Strategic policy for the conduct of the war, 1942-1945 (Box 24)
    Includes Cooke, C. M. "Functions of the Offices of Strategic Services," 1942 November 26; "Strategic Policy of the United States for the Conduct of the War," 1942 November 27; Cooke, C. M. "Basic Strategic Concept for 1943," 1942 December 28; Joint Planners. "Global Estimate of the Situation," 1943 April 28; Cooke, C. M. "Conduct of the War in 1943-1944," comments to Admiral King attached, 1943 May 5; and "U.S. - British Strategy," circa 1943.
  - U.S. Fleet. Pacific Conference, minutes of meetings, 1943-1945
  - U.S. Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba, 1934-1937
    Includes Cooke, C. M. "Report on Projects for Supplying Water to Naval Station, Guantanamo Bay, Cuba," 1935 August 20, and "Water Supply for the Naval Station, Guantanamo," 1937 September 26.
  - U.S. Navy. Submarine Division Eleven, Pearl Harbor, 1931-1933
    Includes Cooke, C. M. "Organization and Employment of Submarines at Pearl Harbor," 1932 June 17.
  - U.S. relations (military) with U.S.S.R., 1942-1945
    - General
    - Operation Lockup
  - U.S.S. S-5 submarine, sinking and rescue of crew (September 1-3, 1920), eyewitness accounts and related material, 1920-1940 (Box 25)
  - White House meeting on the naval efforts in the Pacific, 1945 May 17
    - General
    - Talk by C. M. Cooke
  - Miscellaneous
- COMMERCE INTERNATIONAL CHINA, SPECIAL TECHNICIAN PROGRAM (STP) TO THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA PROJECT FILE, 1949-1954 (Boxes 26-29)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, lists, diagrams, contracts, agreements, financial records, plans, maps, and charts related to a project, coordinated by Cooke, to assist the organization, training, and equipment maintenance programs of the military services of the Republic of China (Taiwan). Arranged alphabetically by subseries.
  - Contracts and agreements (Box 26)
  - Documents related to the history of the Special Technician Program, arranged with a table of contents by C. M. Cooke, 1949-1951
  - Documents related to the Mao (Mow) - Hsiang Case and 3" Shells involving Chinese military procurement, arranged with a partial table of contents by C. M. Cooke, 1950-1951
  - Employment classification lists
  - Financial records, 1950-1952
  - Maps
  - Personnel files
    Access
    RESTRICTED until 2025
  - Personnel rosters
  - Plans and reports of military maneuvers and exercises, 1950-1951
  - Project correspondence, 1950-1954
  - Technical memoranda, inspection reports, and correspondence related to the organization, training, and equipment maintenance programs of the Republic of China, 1950-1951
    - General
    - Chinese Navy
      - General
      - 1950
        - June
        - July
        - August (Box 27)
        - September
        - October
        - November
        - December
      - 1951
        - January
        - February
        - March (Box 28)
        - April
        - May
        - June
        - July
        - August
    - Chinese Air Force
    - Chinese Marine Corps
    - Chinese Army (Ground Forces)
      - Report by General O. T. Pfeiffer, with comments by C. M. Cooke, 1950 November 4
      - Reports by R. A. Baker, with select list of documents by C. M. Cooke
      - Reports by A. B. Ewing, with select list of documents by C. M. Cooke
    - Chinese Engineer Corps
  - Miscellaneous reports, memoranda, and charts, 1950-1951
    - General (Box 29)
    - Cooke, C. M. "Composition of Naval Advisory Group," analysis submitted to U.S. Military Advisory Assistance Group (MAAG), 1951 May 14
    - "Estimate of the Situation of the Chinese Communist Forces as of June 15, 1950," photoprints of report from Commodore Kao to C. M. Cooke (?)
    - "History of Chinese Army in Taiwan,", 1951
    - "Information about Chinese Navy,", 1950 or 1951
    - "Military Establishment of the Republic of China in Taiwan - 1951,"
    - Pawley, William E. Memorandum for General of the Army, George C. Marshall, undated
    - Shah, K. C. "The Chinese Air Force,", 1951
- INGALLS TAIWAN SHIPBUILDING AND DRY DOCK COMPANY (AFFILIATE OF CHINA INTERNATIONAL FOUNDATION AND INGALLS TAIWAN SHIPBUILDING CORPORATION) PROJECT FILE, 1956-1961 (Boxes 30-31)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial statements, publicity releases, organizational charts, and diagrams related to a project, in which Cooke participated, to increase the productive capacity of shipyard facilities in Taiwan. Arranged alphabetically by subseries.
  - Correspondence of C. M. Cooke
    - General (Box 30)
    - Unidentified
    - Barslaag, Karl, 1957
    - Chen, Cheng, 1958
    - Chiang, Kai-shek, 1957
    - Chiang, (Madame) Kai-shek, 1960
    - Coakley, John P., 1961
    - De Carlo, Joseph, 1957-1960
    - Eastland, Senator James O., 1957
    - Gregerson, Magnus I., 1957-1963
    - Hou, Chi-ming, 1957
    - Knowland, Senator William F., 1957
    - Lanier, Monroe B., 1958-1962
    - Lee, S. T., 1961
    - Liu, Hoh-tu, 1961
    - McLaughlin, H. P., 1957-1958
    - Mayo, Fred J., 1960
    - Pao, K. Y., 1960
    - Radford, Admiral Arthur W., 1958
    - Tong, Hollington K., 1958
    - U.S. Department of Commerce. Maritime Administration, 1957
    - U.S. Department of the Navy. Bureau of Ships, 1957
    - U.S. Department of the Navy. Secretary of the Navy, 1957
    - U.S. Development Loan Fund; Dempster McIntosh, undated
    - U.S. Senate. Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee to Investigate the Administration of the Internal Security Act; Robert Morris, 1957
    - Walter, Congressman Francis E., 1957
    - Wang, N. T., 1961
    - Wasson, Houston H., 1958-1960
    - Wei, C. C., 1957-1960
    - Yeh, George K. C., Minister of Foreign Affairs, Republic of China, 1957
    - Yen, C. K., Minister of Finance, Republic of China, 1960
    - Yu, Ta-wei, 1958
  - Diagram of proposed Ingalls Taiwan shipyard, 1957 January 17
  - List of officers of Ingalls Taiwan Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, 1957 April 8
  - Organizational charts and diagrams
    - Inter-company relationships, 1957 April 1
    - China International Foundation, 1957 April 9
    - Ingalls Taiwan Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, 1957 March 12
  - Project correspondence
    - 1956
    - 1957
    - 1958
    - 1959
    - 1960
    - Undated
  - Project news reports, American and Chinese press (in translation)
    - 1957 (Box 31)
    - 1958
    - 1959
    - 1960
    - Undated
  - Project records (reports, memoranda, minutes of meetings, financial statements, and agreements)
    - 1956
    - 1957
    - 1958
    - 1959
    - 1960
    - Undated
  - Taiwan steel mill project documents
    - Correspondence, memoranda, and agreements of Kaiser Engineers and Constructors and Engineers Tanker Corporation, 1958-1959
    - "Feasibility Report on a Proposed Steel Mill in Taiwan, China," prepared by Kaiser Engineers Constructors, 1959 June 11
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILE, circa 1937-1961 (Boxes 32-35)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, charts, histories, newsletters, news clippings, notes, speeches, papers of congressional hearings, rosters, offprints, and other typewritten, mimeograph, printed, and photocopied material, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Aid Refugee Chinese Intellectuals, Inc., 1952 (Box 32)
  - Air power - naval
  - American-Asian Educational Exchange, Inc., 1959
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to Free China, 1961
  - American China Policy Association, 1949-1959
  - American Coalition of Patriotic Societies, 1959
  - Atomic energy
  - Bombers
  - Bombing, aerial
  - Chiang, Kai-shek - Addresses, statements, interviews
  - China
    - Air defenses, military, 1951
    - Military affairs, 1945-1947
    - Politics and government, 1937-1957
  - China International Foundation, 1956
  - China Merchants Steam Navigation Co., Ltd.
  - Chinese in the United States, circa 1957-1958
  - Committee for Freedom for All People, 1960
  - Committee for the Voice of Free China, 1954
  - Committee of One Million Against the Admission of Communist China to the United Nations, 1958-1958
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding Anti-Communist China, 1949
  - Communism
    - General, 1948-1960
    - China
      - General
      - U.S. War Department. Military Intelligence Division. "The Chinese Communist Movement,", 1945 July 5
    - Taiwan
  - Constitution Party (California), 1959
  - European War, 1914-1918 - Submarine campaign
  - Foreign correspondents in Taiwan
  - General Electric Company, 1955
  - Guatemala - United Nations debate, 1954
  - Guerillas - China, circa 1950
  - Hartmann, Arkadius - Biographical material
  - John Birch Society, 1961
  - King, Ernest J. - Biographical material
    Includes Whitehill, Walter Muir. "A Postscript to Fleet Admiral King: A Naval Record," Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society, Vol. 70 (1950-1953), 203-226, offprint.
  - Kohlberg, Alfred - Biographical material
  - Korean War, 1950-1953 - Armistice
  - Latin America, 1960
  - Luce, Stephen B. - Bibliographic essay
  - Malayan Chinese Association, 1949-1951
  - Mao, Tse-tung
  - Military justice - Uniform Code, 1950
  - Patriotism (Box 33)
  - Political opinion
    - Our Country, 1958
    - Right: A Monthly Newsletter of, by and for the American Rightwing, 1958
    - Task Force, 1957
  - Sea-power, 1940
  - Shanghai - Map, 1940s
  - Ships
  - Taiwan (Republic of China)
    - General
    - Climate and weather, 1944
    - Foreign relations
      - General, 1950-1959
      - Russia
    - Forest policy, 1950
    - Military affairs
    - Oceanography, 1944
    - Politics and government
  - Technical assistance, Russian China, 1950
  - Tsingtao American School, 1948
  - United Nations - Admission of Communist China
  - United States
    - Armed Forces
      - Amphibious Training Command
      - Far East Command, 1950
      - Organization
        - 1950
        - 1952
        - 1953
        - 1955
        - 1956
        - 1957
        - 1958 (Box 34)
        - Undated
    - Defense - Technical and military aspects
    - Foreign aid
      - Taiwan (Republic of China)
    - Foreign relations
      - General
      - Far Eastern policy, 1946-1960
    - Military policy
    - National security
  - U.S. Air Force - Congressional hearings, 1949 (Box 35)
  - U.S. Information Service
  - U.S. Marine Corps - Clothing
  - U.S. Military Advisory Assistance Group (MAAG) - Roster, 1951
  - U.S. Naval Academy. Class of 1910 - Fiftieth reunion
  - U.S. Navy
    - General
    - Guided missiles
    - History
    - Personnel
      - Regulations
      - Roster, 1961
    - Ship transfers to China - Public Law 512
    - Submarines
  - U.S.S. Luce - Commissioning ceremonies, 1961
  - Ventura, California - Harbor project
  - World Affairs Council of Northern California - China Conference, 1950
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - Aerial operations, American
    - History
    - Military strategy
  - Miscellaneous
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE (Box 35)
  Autobiographical and biographical material, including vitae, biographical sketches, and correspondence, concerning Cooke and the Cooke family history. Also includes awards, citations, and diplomas received by Cooke.
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Photo file)
  Contains 85 photos and 20 duplicate photos in 2 envelopes.
  - 5 photos and 3 duplicates of Cooke with Chiang Kai-shek and/or Madame Chiang, circa 1950s; 1 photo of Cooke with Hansen Baldwin, Robert Patterson, and Lewis B. Hershey; 1 photo of Mrs. C. M. Cooke; 1 photo i.d. card of Cooke; 1 photo of Cooke with British naval officers, circa 1940s; 1 photo of unidentified U.S. naval officer; 7 photos of Ingalls Taiwan Shipbuilding project; 4 photo of Alfred and Ida Kohlberg at the National Defense Medical Center, Taiwan, 1953; 17 photos of Cooke alone and on various social occasions, undated (Envelope A)
  - 15 photos of Cooke with various Nationalist Chinese military personnel; 11 photos and 17 duplicates of nationalist Chinese military activities; 21 photos of various people, places and things, perhaps in China and Taiwan, circa 1946-1951 (Envelope B)
- DECLASSIFIED RECORDS, 1932-1957 (Reading room workstation, Box 37)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2010 release of records, 1945
    - "Capabilities and Intentions of the U.S.S.R. in the Post-War Period," R&A No. 2669, Research and Analysis Branch, Office of Strategic Services, 1945 January 5 (Reading room workstation)
      Available as a PDF file.
  - 2011 release of records, 1932-1957 (Box 37)
    - Unclassified letter received and Cooke will, 1932-1953 (Box-folder 37: 1)
    - Naval career office file, 1942-1945 (Box-folder 37: 2)
    - Commerce International China file, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 37: 3-9)
    - Ingalls Taiwan file, 1957 (Box-folder 37: 10)